# **Mikhail Pchelintsev**

+7 (909) 650-6727 | Michael.Pchelintsev@gmail.com

Sr. Data Scientist / Data Science Team Lead



### **OVERVIEW**

Applied data science has been an area of passion and the main focus in recent years, while several DS projects have been fully implemented into commercial operation.

Additionally, there is a successful experience in IT product and project management obtained in the big-4 consulting for industry-leading companies.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### **ID Finance**, Asia (idfinance.com)

Sr. data scientist, June 2022 - Present

• Implementing financial models for debt management

## Sberbank PJSC, Moscow, Russia (<a href="https://sber.ru/">https://sber.ru/</a>)

RND lead / Sr. data scientist, Mar. 2021 - May 2022

- The task was to improve mortgage issuance support:
  - extracting the call center employee skills (NLP based);
  - optimal distribution of tasks to reduce labor costs and increase sales of services;
- The solution was to launch an Agile research process with rapid AB-experimenting; a team of 3 DS and 1 DE was managed. A product backlog was built and prioritized;
- Several DS models were created, such as forecasting task complexity and time, task prioritization, and task to employee recommendation;

**Results:** cross-sales increased by up to 30% (depending on the product); labor intensity reduced by 25%; comprehensive monitoring for the task distribution system was designed.

### Data scientist, Jul. 2019 - Mar. 2021

- The main task was to introduce NLP analysis of the corporate sale process;
- UI pricing tool was designed according to business demands. To provide its functionality, realty pricing, sales forecast, and realty look-alike models were implemented;
- NLP analysis was based on text classification and named entity recognition models;

**Results:** mortgage approval was automated; the pricing accuracy was increased by 5% compared to the former process; the NLP approach allowed to define reasons for client refusals to take credits.

### Business analyst, Jan. 2019 - Mar. 2019

• The goal of our consulting team (Strategy Partners Group) was to develop the city strategy till 2050 for a CIS country capital;

**Results:** the analytical research was performed by defining the cities for benchmarking.

## Ernst & Young, Moscow, Russia (<a href="https://www.ey.com/">https://www.ey.com/</a>)

### Senior consultant, Sep. 2017 - Jan. 2019

- Automating and designing operational processes for the major retailer in Kazakhstan (> 150 shops) to improve service level at shops and increase shelf presence of goods;
- The project stream of 3 analysts was managed; new processes were designed and piloted in client shops providing training for linear personnel; AB-test analytics was made;
- Additionally, several innovative solutions were implemented, such as a stock inventory planning model and a monitoring tool for quality control;

**Results:** the employee personal motivation system was introduced based on new quality control and stock inventory management processes.

### Staff consultant, Sep. 2016 - Sep. 2017

- Automating and designing operational processes for major industrial companies to reduce costs and increase profits;
- The business processes analytics and solution visualization were the core responsibilities; as well as leading project streams of 3-4 people, communicating and presenting results to clients;

**Results:** the production planning model was created for a big mining company; the cloud platform was designed for a big agriculture company (supporting transport monitoring and quality control).

# Danfoss A/S, Russia, China, Denmark (<a href="https://www.danfoss.com/">https://www.danfoss.com/</a>)

### Business analyst, Sep. 2015 - Sep. 2016

- Supply and demand forecasting; focusing on supply chain management to reduce lead times and increase stock availability;
- Predictive models were created for sales and safety stock forecasting; the management reporting meetings were started;

**Results:** stock availability was increased by 5% (item on stock when a client wanted to buy).

### <u>Production optimization intern</u>, Sep. 2014 - Sep. 2015

 Practicing and implementing lean manufacturing principles on international shop floors; developing technical solutions and models to optimize production processes;

**Results:** VBA tool for equipment efficiency monitoring was introduced (Moscow Region); the model for equipment changeover planning was created by implementing the article on ant colony algorithm (Tianjin, China).

# Profi.ru, Moscow, Russia (<a href="https://profi.ru/profile/PchelintsevMA/">https://profi.ru/profile/PchelintsevMA/</a>)

### Private math tutor, Sep. 2010 - Sep. 2014

- Tutoring students for math state and university exams (around 40 students from schools and the first years of universities);
- The client satisfaction rating was 4.9.

### **EDUCATION**

### **Bauman Moscow State Technical University, 2007-2014**

- Power engineering; low-temperature physics; diploma project to design movable system for natural gas liquefaction;
- GPA: 4.9 out of 5.

### ADDITIONAL EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Kaggle competition expert, 2019-2022, <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/mishanyap">https://www.kaggle.com/mishanyap</a>;
- KarpovCourses, HardML, 2021

Ranking and matching; Uplift-modeling; Dynamic pricing with multi-armed bandits; ABtesting;

• Stepik.org, 2019-2020

Neural nets and computer vision; Programming algorithms: theory and practice; Advanced statistics:

- Coursera.org, 2018, Major data science specialization from Yandex and MIPT;
- ENSAM University of Lille, France, 2013, future transportation workshops.

### ADDITIONAL SKILLS

- Professional use of Atlassian JIRA, Confluence, MS Office (PowerPoint, Excel, Project),
  Miro;
- DS domain experience in Classical ML, Pricing, Recommendations, NLP, Deep Learning,
  Uplift-modeling, Reinforcement learning (multi-armed bandits), AB-tests;
- Practical use of Python, Pycharm, LightGBM, CatBoost, Pytorch, Keras, Scikit-learn,
  Pandas, Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, Optuna;
- Practical use of SQL, Hive, Spark, Postgres, MySQL, DataGrip;
- Experience in Git, Docker, REST API, ELK, Linux, Visual Basic for Applications (VBA), AutoCAD;
- Structuring and presentation designing, interviewing skills.